Finding Aid for the Leadership In Nashville Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
Leadership In Nashville Collection
Special Collections Manuscripts and Rare Books
MSS.0585
.02 linear_feet
Biography/History
This was a special project chosen by a History of Nashville Class of Senior Citizens and the results of their topic on Nashville’s Hundred Greatest Citizens. These people were selected on the basis of their contributions to city, state, or nation. By agreement, no one was included whose death occurred less than twenty years before the class.
The list is the product of the combined judgment of the class. The teacher, Alfred Leland Crabb, reserved the right of veto. In all, 154 men and women were nominated. The list was gradually reduced to a minimum of 116. Prolonged effort was made to lower the number to the 100 originally agreed upon, but it was futile.
In 1984, the class project was transferred from the Peabody Library to Special Collections.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains one manuscript item with 41 pages, titled Leadership in Nashville. It contains a listing of 116 of the most prominent citizens in Nashville leadership, with brief accompanying biographical sketches. The following people are listed:
- Adelicia Hayes Acklen, 1817-1889
  Social leader, gracious hostess
- Adam Gillespie Adams, 1829-1895
  Merchant and banker
- Edward Emerson Barnard, 1857-1923
  Astronomy
- Washington Barrow, 1807-1866
  Editor and Congressman
- John Meredith Bass, 1804-1878
  Lawyer, banker, planter, twice mayor
- Jere Baxter, 1852-1904
  Builder, Tennessee Central Railroads
- John Bell, 1797-1869
  Lawyer, statesman, orator, political leader
- William T. Berry, 1813-1889
  Publisher and bookseller
- John Diell Blanton, 1859-1933
  President of Ward Belmont College
- William, Kirkman Bowling, 1808-1885
  Physician, medical editor, Dean
- Richard Henry Boyd, 1843-1938
  Negro banker, publisher, editor, preacher
- William T. Briggs, 1829-1894
  Surgeon
- Michael Burns, 1813-1896
  Businessman, railroader, banker
- George Washington Campbell, 1769-1848
  Lawyer, judge, Congressman, Senator
- William Carroll, 1788-1844
  Merchant, soldier, Governor of Tennessee
- John Catron, 1786-1865
  Justice of Supreme Court/United States
- Benjamin Franklin Cheatham, 1820-1886
  Farmer, Confederate General
- Joel Owsley Cheek, 1852-1935
  Merchant, industrial pioneer
- Ann Robertson Cockrill, 1788-1872
  Pioneer, first school teacher in Mid-TN
- Mark Robertson Cockrill, 1788-1872
  Surveyor, agriculturalist
- Edmund Whitefoord Cole, 1827-1900
  Railroader, banker, Methodist layman
- Washington Cooper, 1802-1899
  Portrait artist
- Thomas Brown Craighead, 1750-1825
  Presbyterian preacher, teacher
- Nathaniel Cross, 1802-1866
  Educator, orator, classical scholar
- John Hibbett DeWitt, 1872-1937
  Lawyer, judge, historian
- Jacob McGavock Dickinson, 1851-1928
  Lawyer, Cabinet Member
- John Donelson, 1725-1785
  Surveyor, Brigadier General U.S. Army
- Mary C. Dorris, 1850-1924
  Hermitage preservation
- Will Allen Dromgoole, 1860-1934
  Journalist, poet
- William Lafland Dudley, 1859-1914
  Dean, chairman of Athletics at Vanderbilt
- George Dury, 1817-1893
  Artist
- John Todd Edgar, 1792-1860
  Presbyterian minister
- Collins D. Elliott, 1810-1899
  Educator, preacher, civil leader
- Joseph T. Elliston, Merchant, Methodist layman
- Paul Fitzsimmons Eve, 1806-1877
  Surgeon, teacher, editor
- Andrew Ewing, 1813-1864
  Lawyer, orator, statesman
- Edwin Hickman Ewing, 1809-1902
  Lawyer, Congressman, orator
- Francis Brinley Fogg, 1795-1880
  Attorney, public spirited citizen
- Mary Middleton Rutledge Fogg, 1800-1872
  Cultured and gracious lady, author
- Ephraim Hubbard Foster, 1794-1854
  Attorney, Whig politician, U.S. Senator
- Landon Cabell Garland, 1810-1895
  First Chancellor of Vanderbilt
- Augustin Gattinger, 1825-1903
  Physician, botanist
- Alexander Little Page Green, 1806-1874
  Methodist minister
- Anne Rodgers Grundy, 1779-1847
  Mother of 12, active in church/city
- Felix Grundy, 1777-1840
  Lawyer, statesman, orator
- William Giles Harding, 1808-1886
  Agriculturalist, stock-breeder
- Adolphus Heiman, 1809-1862
  Architect, soldier
- Edward Dickson Hicks, 1831-1894
  Businessman, farmer, civil leader
- John Melchior Hull, 1797-1870
  Merchant, businessman
- Robert Boyte Crawford Howell, 1801-1868
  Baptist minister, author, editor
- Alfred Hume, 1808-1854
  Educator, first superintendent schools
- William Hume, 1770-1833
  Clergyman, educator
- Andrew Jackson, 1767-1845
  Seventh President of United States
- Howell Edmunds Jackson, 1832-1895
  Lawyer, Assoc. Justice of Supreme Court
- Rachel Donelson Jackson, 1766-1828
  Wife of Andrew Jackson
- James Franklin Jarman, 1867-1937
  Businessman, philanthropist, General Shoe
- James Weldon Johnson, 1871-1938
  Negro writer of plays and operas
- Joseph Buckner Killebrew, 1831-1906
  Scientist, author, editor, agriculturalist
- James Hampton Kirkland, 1859-1939
  Second Chancellor of Vanderbilt
- John McCormick Lea, 1818-1903
  Lawyer, jurist, scholar
- Rabbi Isadore Lewinthal, 1849-1923
  Rabbi, community leader
- Eugene Castner Lewis, 1845-1917
  Engineer, architect, railroad executive
- John Berrien Lindsley, 1822-1897
  Educator, physician, clergyman
- Philip Lindsley, 1786-1855
  Educator, clergyman, scholar
- David Lipscomb, 1832-1918
  Farmer, teacher, preacher, editor
- Lee Fefferson Loventhal, 1875-1940
  Businessman, philanthropist
- John Berry McFerrin, 1807-1887
  Methodist preacher, editor
- Randall William McGavock, 1826-1863
  Politician, diarist, author, soldier
- William McKendree, 1757-1835
  Methodist Circuit Rider, Bishop
- Boyd McNairy, 1785-1856
  Physician, prominent citizen
- Holland Nimmons McTyeire, 1824-1889
  Methodist Bishop, Vanderbilt Founder
- Thomas Lafayette Maddin, 1826-1908
  Physician, surgeon, professor
- Return Jonathan Meigs, 1801-1891
  Lawyer, jurist, scholar, author
- Richard Pius Miles, 1791-1860
  Priest/Bishop Roman Catholic Church
- William Nichol, 1800-1878
  Businessman, banker, broker
- John Overton, 1766-1833
  Pioneer, legal authority, jurist
- Bruce Ryburn Payne
  Educator
- William Harold Payne, 1836-1907
  Scholar, administrator, education
- James Dace Plunkett, 1839-1919
  Physician, public health, sanitation
- James Knox Polk, 1795-1849
  Eleventh President of United States
- Sara Childress Polk, 1803-1891
  Wife of James Knox Polk
- George Washington Price, 1830-1892
  Minister, educator
- James Priestly, 1740-1821
  Classical scholar, educator
- Charles Todd Quintard, 1824-1898
  Physician, Episcopal Bishop
- Charlotte Reeves Robertson, 1751-1843
  Wife of James Robertson
- Duncan Robertson, 1770-1833
- Felix Robertson, 1781-1865
  Physician, community leader
- James Robertson, 1742-1814
  Nashville founder, frontiersman
- Henry Middleton Rutledge, 1775-1844
  Lawyer, planter
- Samuel Seay, 1784-1864
  Merchant, Presbyterian elder
- John Shelby, 1786-1859
  Physician
- Baxter Smith, 1832-
  Attorney
- Edward Bushrod Stahlman, 1843-1936
  Newspaper publisher, railroad executive
- Vernon K. Stevenson
  Pioneer in railroad building
- William Stockell, 1815-1888
  Merchant, originator of Nashville Fire Dept.
- William Strickland, 1787-1854
  Architect, engineer, painter
- Wilkins Tannehill, 1787-1858
  Businessman, scholar, historian
- Henry Teitlebaun, 1871-1940
  Merchant, community servant
- Gates Phillips Thurston, 1835-1914
  Soldier, lawyer, banker, author
- Herbert Cushing Tolman, 1865-1937
  Classical scholar, archeologist, author
- John Trimbel, 1812-1884
  Lawyer, scholar
- Girard Troost, 1776-1850
  Scientist
- James Isaac Vance, 1862-1939
- William E. Ward, 1829-1887
  Minister, Founder of Ward’s Seminary
- James Carthwright Warner, 1829-1887
  Businessman, manufacturer, philanthropist
- Samuel Watkins, 1794-1882
  Contractor, manufacturer, philanthropist
- Robert Weakley, 1764-1845
  Farmer, surveyor, land owner
- James Whitsitt, 1771-1849
  Missionary
- Dempsey Weaver, 1815-1880
  Financier, philanthropist
- George Leonard White, 1838-1895
  Educator, creator of Fisk Jubilee Singers
- Charles K. Winston
  Physician, professor
- John Wesley Work Sr., 1871-1925
  Composer, educator
- Felix Kirk Zollicoffer, 1812-1862
  Editor, Congressman, soldier